Okay בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is כ"ו *chaf vav*,
and we are caught up. We're going to start with some משנה
Mishnah *mishna*. I should just mention very briefly two things from yesterday.
One was, as some people might have seen, Charlie sent out by
email about the jumping elephants here according to תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*. When
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* talks about these bundles of twigs, רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says it's just walking on top of the twigs, so it's
a הגבהה hagbah *hagbaha* that you get the elephant to, you know,
to move off of the ground. It is interesting, you know, again
that you don't need to actually lift it to do הגבהה hagbahah,
*hagbaha*. And then there's that question about three טפחים *tefachim* or one
טפח tefach *tefach*. But תוספות Tosfos. *Tosafos* says you hold some type
of a twig with a leaf up high and the elephant jumps
for it. And as Charlie, who just walked in, pointed, you know,
a number of people pointed out yesterday, elephants don't jump. Apparently, Natan
Slifkin, who does all this stuff on animals or whatever, wrote a
whole essay about that, about that mistaken assumption about whether elephants jump
and whether תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* ever even saw an elephant. And he
actually said that somebody tried to defend תוספות *Tosafos* by saying that
תוספות *Tosafos* was talking about an elephant on a trampoline. So go
figure that one out. That's a much more reasonable explanation. The other
thing that I wanted to say, which I got rushed at the
end of yesterday, is we were talking about a hierarchy of קניינים
kinyanim *kinyanim*, right? So if you say הגבהה hagbahah, *hagbaha* works, you
know, you do הגבהה hagbahah, *hagbaha* by בהמה דקה *behemah dakah*, what
you're saying is because you're emphasizing what's considered the top level is
what you're saying is the other lower קניינים kinyanim *kinyanim* don't work.
משיכה meshicha *Meshichah* doesn't work, מסירה mesira. *mesirah* doesn't work, and so
on. So it's important to understand what's considered to be the stronger
one. So when you read the statement in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
that מסירה mesirah *mesirah* works by בהמה גסה behema gassa, *behemah gassah*,
is that saying מסירה mesirah *mesirah* only and not משיכה meshicha, *meshichah*?
That's how רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reads it. Or you're saying even מסירה
mesira, *mesirah* and certainly משיכה meshikhah, *meshichah* works, you know, and there's
the question about, you know, what sort of is the hierarchy. Anyway,
but the assumption is once you generally פוסקן *pasken* that a number
of קניינים kinyanim *kinyanim* work, like by a בהמה דקה *behemah dakah*,
if you פוסקן *pasken* that משיכה meshikhah, *meshichah* works, הגבהה hagbahah *hagbaha*
works, etc., then you could use any one, you know, whichever you
know you have the range available to you. But based on some
other סוגיא *sugya*, there's a position of the רשב"ם *Rashbam* that in
some places, you know, if you have, if you can choose between
מסירה *mesirah* and משיכה meshikhah. *meshichah*, you have to do משיכה meshikhah.
*meshichah*, like you have to do the stronger one. And if you
did the weaker one it wouldn't work, if you have both available
to you.
And תוספות *Tosafos* really like strongly objects to that and it's just
such a good line, or רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* does, I just
wanted to read it inside. So if you look at it, it's
like ten lines before the תוספות *Tosafos* ends, the line starts with
the word למקניי *l'miknayei*. So תוספות *Tosafos* says, right, or like if
you look one line above, וכיון דאפשר במשיכה שהוא קנין kinyan. חשוב
*v'keivan d'efshar b'meshichah shehu kinyan chashuv* in a certain type of a
place like a סימטא *simta*, whatever, where you could do משיכה meshicha.
*meshichah*, which is this better קנין kinyan *kinyan*, לאו אורח דארעא למקניי
במסירה שהוא קנין kinyan גרוע *lav orach d'ara l'miknayei b'mesirah shehu kinyan
garua*, then מסירה *mesirah* wouldn't work, okay. And then he says רבינו
*Rabbeinu*, so he says if you have to, if you can choose
and in a certain place you can do both, you have to
do משיכה meshicha. *meshichah*. משיכה meshicha *Meshichah* is better than מסירה *mesirah*.
So he says רבינו תם היטחה פירוש הרשב"ם *Rabbeinu Tam hitcha peirush
haRashbam*. רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* asked this, וכי מצוות הן *v'chi mitzvos
hein* משיכה meshicha? *meshichah*, מסירה *mesirah*? Are they like מצוות *mitzvos* שמבטלו
זו את זו *she'mevatlo zu es zu* that doing like one מצוה
*mitzvah* is מבטלו *mevatlo* the other one, and you know ושאין לעשות
אלא ella, מן המובחר *v'she'ein la'asos ela min hamuvchar*, you have to
do the best מצוה *mitzvah*, you have to do the מצוה מן
המובחר *mitzvah min hamuvchar*? You can't do the weaker קנין kinyan *kinyan*.
It's you know, who cares? It's not like an idea that there's
some ritual value or even some legal value. If it effects the
transfer, what difference does it make if it's what's normally considered a
weaker קנין kinyan. *kinyan* or stronger קנין kinyan *kinyan*? If we פוסקן
*pasken* both work, why should you be forced to do something that
is considered normally to be the better one, right? The best, that's
not relevant. If we פוסקן *pasken* in a particular case both work,
you should be able to choose either one. Anyway, I just thought
it was such a great line that our קניינים kinyanim *kinyanim*, you
know, are they מצוות שמבטלו זו את זו *mitzvos she'mevatlo zu es
zu*? Presumably
the the logic of the רשב"ם *Rashbam* is is you know, yes,
that in a certain type of a that if the idea of
a קנין kinyan *kinyan* is to demonstrate בעלות *balos* and ownership and
you're able to demonstrate more meaningful ownership, right, especially if you think
like תוספות *Tosafos* says that מסירה *mesirah* is very weak. Meaning משיכה
meshicha, *meshichah* is strong, הגבהה hagbaha. *hagbaha* might be stronger, but they're
both strong קניינים kinyanim *kinyanim*. So you do משיכה meshicha *meshichah*, it
doesn't mean like it's not good because you could have done הגבהה
Hagbaha *hagbaha*. That was a very good demonstration of ownership. But מסירה
*mesirah* seems to תוספות *Tosafos* says is like a weaker demonstration, you're
just holding on to the reins. It's not something that's demonstrated like
full, you're not picking it up, you're not drawing it to you.
It's a weaker type of a thing. So by if it's the
only thing available then in a vacuum it can work, but when
there's other types of ways of demonstrating ownership available to you, then
that actually relative to that means that you didn't do anything meaningful.
In this context it's not a meaningful act because you could, if
you were really the owner, you would have done something more significant.
So anyway, that's an interesting question in thinking of the hierarchy, are
there cases where you should do you know where where because you
have both available you're supposed to do the higher one.
More more of a less binary
view, yes that you either you're the owner or you're not, right,
right, it was a switch.
Aha. Interesting. Right. And it's also not binary in the sense that
I've talked about a hierarchy, but one could imagine, one could imagine
where you say that some קנינים kinyanim. are just are are not
really, you know, like, relevant to the others. Like in the מסירה
משיכה mesira meshicha question, you could have said משיכה meshicha. doesn't work
by certain animals because they're, like a horse, fundamentally what ownership is
demonstrated is by taking the reins and not, you know, by, or
whatever, you know. And other types of things that's only משיכה, meshicha
not מסירה. Anyway, but that's all, but that is the general sense
that there is a hierarchy and that if you say that the
lower thing can work, obviously the higher one can work. But if
you say you have to do like, you know, הגבהה Hagbaha by
בהמה גסה, which is like what, you know, the whole thing with
the elephant, רב יוסף Rav Yosef would say, presumably your point is
to say you can't do the lower level קנינים. kinyanim Okay. Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we move from מטלטלין metaltelin
from cattle to land. So let's take a look at the משנה
Mishnah. on the top of כו עמוד ב. kaf-vav amud bet. נכסים
שיש להם אחריות נקנים בכסף בשטר ובחזקה. nechasim sheyesh lahem achrayut niknim
be-kesef bi-shtar u-ve-chazaka.
Objects that have אחריות, achrayut, that have liens, which basically means real
estate and land. I believe that it, that the thing is that
in the older משניות, Mishnayot, the word, you know, that was the
way of referring to קרקע. karka. They didn't use the word קרקע,
karka, it was נכסים שיש להם אחריות. nechasim sheyesh lahem achrayut. Sometimes
you have these more
antiquated phrases which really demonstrates the sense that this is a very
like older, this is an older משנה. Mishnah You have it also
I think in, ah, I'm trying to remember, there's an early משנה
Mishnah in בבא קמא Bava Kamma that's similar about how it refers
to הקדש hekdesh and חולין chullin and it also uses like earlier
terms which went out of use sort of later on. Anyway, it's
also, as we mentioned when we began the מסכת, Masechet, these משניות
Mishnayot that are all about this, these degrees of קנינים and very
well organized, you know, where, you know, a woman, slave, Hebrew slave,
not, you know, you know, עבד כנעני, eved kenaani, this, you know,
cattle, etc., etc., and it's very sort of a tight organization around
a tight theme is a really very early collection of משניות. Mishnayot.
So נכסים שיש להם אחריות nechasim sheyesh lahem achrayut refers to basically
land, real estate, because and they have liens, because when you make
a loan, there's a lien on the real estate. So those, נקנים
בכסף בשטר ובחזקה, niknim be-kesef bi-shtar u-ve-chazaka, are acquired with money, with
a writ, with a document, and with חזקה, chazaka, with taking possession.
There's actually a very interesting debate about כסף kessef because normally you
would assume כסף kessef means when you pay the full value. But
because by קידושי אשה Kiddushei Isha we say כסף kessef is symbolic
and it's a פרוטה, prutah, that becomes a whole interesting question about
whether if you pay the first פרוטה prutah towards the purchase of
the land, whether that becomes a קנין כסף. kinyan kessef. And you
could conceptualize that as two ways. You could say if I mean,
you could say it doesn't, you have to pay the full amount.
But if you say it does, you could conceptualize it in two
ways. You could conceptualize it as you do have to pay the
full amount, but as soon as I pay one dollar and then
then what we're really saying is we consider it like I paid
the rest and you lent me back the money. And now I
have a debt on the money. Not because I haven't paid, not
because it's the unpaid purchase price, but because essentially you've advanced me
the money. So that's one way of conceptualizing it. Another way of
conceptualizing it is no, as soon as you pay any amount towards
it, that effects the קנין. kinyan. So that's interesting, you know, what
כסף kessef means once we say כסף kessef means a פרוטה prutah
by קידושי אשה. Kiddushei Isha. Okay. Yeah. And then does he mean
is that a debate יצא משכיר תחילה סוף yatza maskir techilla-sof that
kind of thing?
I mean, maybe it's brought in, but it's, I mean, there's obviously
some parallel there. Yeah.
We had the same discussion by the קנין kinyan, for אשה, isha,
right? That like if you said that you were going to give
her X amount.
Oh, right. The guy who was counting out the money and before
he finished. Yeah. That's actually a good point. Right. The guy said
I'm going to marry you with 50 whatever and he was counting
out the money and whether he meant the פרוטה אחרונה. prutah achrona.
Right. That's actually more of a parallel. Right. So that's that's a
good point. But that was like when you're in the middle of,
you know, it was clear the process was handing over the money.
Right. But you're right, you sort of conceptually here, like even without
that being in the process, you sort of see it as as
that way. Yeah.
It's not, it's not the same as land obviously, but there's a
משנה mishnah. in the last chapter of שביעית Shevi'it where so a
merchant who sells something and doesn't get paid right away, that kind
of debt is not treated the same as.
Right. Right. That's another excellent point. Right. If you haven't paid up
the balance of what you owe to a merchant, is that a
הלוואה halva'ah that gets annulled during שמיטה Shmita or an unpaid debt
through purchase? purchase but not a loan? Right, so those are all
very relevant and interesting. Anyway, before, rather the real question here is,
is that do we learn from קידושי אשה kidushei isha that it's
the first dollar that that's symbolically is enough or is it fundamentally
the full amount? Okay, ובשטר uv'shtar which we'll see what that is
in the גמרא Gemara but basically the מוכר mocher writes on a
document שדי מכורה לך, sadi mekhurah lakh, I am giving you my
and hands over the document. ובחזקה uv'chazakah which we will see some
sense of physical taking possession and here of course is why קרקע
karka is different than מטלטלין metaltelin because מטלטלין metaltelin is movable and
therefore you can actually do things to move it, draw it into
you, raise it up and so on. משיכה, meshicha הגבהה, hagbahah, this
you cannot do and there are other things that are more signified.
Also just the question about how do you establish ownership, like how
do you not how do you transfer ownership, but how do you
presume
ownership by chat- the normal- what is it, possession is nine-tenths of
the law, which in the גמרא Gemara. terminology is חזקה כל מה
שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא שלו. chazakah kol mah shetachat yad adam
harei hu shelo. There's a presumption that anything that's under your control
is yours, meaning if it's in your pocket, on your person, in
your house. So that's why those are the types of קניינים kinyanim
also that work by מטלטלין metaltelin because we normally presume that if
you're controlling it and it's on your person and in your house,
etc., חצר, chatzer, all those types of things, יד, yad, הגבהה, משיכה,
meshicha, that's a presumption of ownership. But by קרקע, karka, just because
you're on somebody's, you're on a piece of land is not a
presumption of ownership. Right? So there's no what are you going to
do that's going to demonstrate the ownership. And some of these things,
like כסף, kesef, is not an ongoing way of demonstrating the ownership,
right? It's a momentary
transaction. חזקה chazakah is more also not an ongoing way because you
do an act and then you walk off of the property. It's
not like it stays in your house like by chattel. But nevertheless,
these are now different ways of demonstrating ownership which are necessary because
you don't have the more sort of certain like the more self-evident
ways or intuitive ways that exist by chattel when it's just on
your person, on your property, you're controlling it and so on. So
that's why you have these things that more focus on the act
of the exchange, the כסף, kesef, the שטר, shtar, and the חזקה,
chazakah, but we will talk about them. Okay, שנכסים שאין להם אחריות,
she'nekhasim she'ein lahem achrayut, now goes on to say the following: שנכסים
שאין להם אחריות, she'nekhasim she'ein lahem achrayut, those that do not have
liens, which means
chattel, like before we were talking about animals, but any type of
inanimate movable object,
אין נקנין אלא במשיכה. ein niknin ella b'meshikhah. That's with משיכה. meshicha
So while by animals we discussed מסירה and הגבהה, etc., here it
says everything because presumably this is now talking more also more generically
also of inanimate objects is all by משיכה. meshicha הגבהה would obviously
also work but מסירה was limited to possibly certain types of animals.
Okay. נכסים שאין להם
אחריות נקנין עם נכסים שיש להם אחריות בכסף בשטר ובחזקה. nekhasim she'ein
lahem achrayut niknin im nekhasim she'yesh lahem achrayut b'kesef b'shtar uv'chazakah. Now
here's another way that you can acquire chattel because which is if
you acquire קרקע karka then with כסף שטר וחזקה kesef shtar v'chazakah
then you can acquire chattel together with it, that קרקע. karka. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to- so basically רב פפא Rav Papa
can be the question. Is it as long as it's on it
or is it not? Okay. So Michael here wants to sell me
his couch and he's also going to sell me his yard. So
if I take possession of the yard, I can also own the
couch. And the question is: does the couch have to be in
the yard or not? So we'll see about that. And then it
reverses directions. וזוקקין v'zokakin now, the chattel to the chattel- so on
the one hand, the land can, if you buy the land the
chattel can be purchased together with the land, can transfer with the
land. On the other hand, if you start with the chattel, it
can schlep along the land in the following way: וזוקקין את הנכסים
שיש להם אחריות להשבע עליהם. v'zokakin et hanekhasim she'yesh lahem achrayut l'hishava
aleihem. You don't take an oath on land. You only take an
oath on chattel. Like if I say you lent me, you stole
some, let's just say, you lent me a hundred dollars, I lent
you a hundred dollars, no, I only took fifty, take a שבועה,
shvuah, מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, etc., I gave you two objects to
watch, you only gave me one object, etc. So if you have
a case about land and it's hard about that, then you would
not take a שבועה. shvuah. But if I got you to take
a שבועה shvuah about chattel, then once I've already forced you to
take a שבועה, shvuah, I can say, and now I want you
to swear to me about this land issue. Okay, and that's called
גלגול שבועה, gilgul shvuah, like a rolling שבועה shvuah that once you
have a, you can obligate a שבועה shvuah in one area, you
can force the person to take a שבועה shvuah on a whole
range of things. In so in one way land schleps along the
chattel when you take possession of the land, it's a way of
transferring chattel, and the chattel schleps along the land if you take
a שבועה shvuah on chattel, you can force a שבועה shvuah on
land as well. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
A lot of things in this
משנה. mishnah בכסף מנלן. b'kesef m'nalan. Where do you know that land
is purchased with money? So אמר חזקיה, amar Chizkiyah, you learn it
from קידושי אשה, kidushei isha, קיחה קיחה, kichah kichah, no the other
way. Anyway, אמר חזקיה אמר קרא שדות בכסף יקנו, amar Chizkiyah amar
kra sadot b'kesef yiknu, because it says you shall purchase fields with
money. And that's a פסוק pasuk in ירמיה. Yirmiyah. Okay. ואימא עד
דאיכא
שטר?
v'eima ad d'ika
shtar?
We'll get to that. I mean תוספות talk about that. ואימא עד
דאיכא שטר, v'eima ad d'ika shtar, and what, maybe you need both
money and a
שטר? shtar? The end of the פסוק pasuk is buy these fields
with money and write it in a writ and sign it and
have witnesses sign it. So it seems like you need both. So
the גמרא Gemara. says no. אי כתיב יקנו לבסוף, Ei ketiv yiknu
levasof, if it said שדות בכסף יקנו וכתוב בספר sadot becheseph yiknu
vechatov basepher
or something like that, then it would be hard grammar, but anyway
כדקאמרת, kedekamart, it would be like you said that the קניין kinyan
is only with both of those combined. השתא דכתיב יקנו מעיקרא, Hashta
dechtiv yiknu me'ikara, שדות בכסף יקנו. sadot becheseph yiknu.
The verb is after the money. Give the money, buy fields with
money. And afterwards, after you've bought the field, write a writ, write
a document. Okay, so כסף קני. kesef kani. So the land, the
money is what takes possession. שטר ראיה בעלמא הוא, Shtar raya be'alma
hu, and the שטר shtar is just as evidence. You want to
have a שטר shtar to prove ownership, but that's not what in
the case of the פסוק, pasuk, that is not what effects the
exchange.
It is true, a שטר shtar can also be used to effect
the transaction, but in this פסוק, pasuk, the שטר shtar was only
for evidence, the כסף kesef was effecting the transaction. Okay. So now
Michael says what about the פסוק pasuk by אברהם? Avraham? Because I
was joking, I was saying let's learn it from קידושי אישה, Kiddushei
Isha, right? Which is obviously that's what's learned out from קרקע. karka.
But that was from אברהם. Avraham. So take a look at תוספות.
אמר קרא בכסף יקנו. Amar kra becheseph yiknu. הדר לא אייתי מקרא
דכתיב גבי עפרון, Hadar lo aiti mikra dechtiv gabei Efron, right? It
says נתתי כסף השדה קח ממני. natati cheseph hasadeh kach mimeni. He's
paying money for it. משום דדילמא האי נמי מנוכרי שכל קניינו בכסף.
Mishum de'dilma hai nami minochri shekol kinyano becheseph. That was from a
non-Jew and there are different, or coming up what why couldn't it
be from...
I don't
know what to say to that. But anyway, there's also the פסוקים
psukim by קידושין Kiddushin about by the father selling it. Right, this
was one of the פסוקים. psukim. But anyway, look, we're also coming
up to פסח Pesach where you sell the חמץ chametz to the
non-Jew and the שטר מכירת חמץ shtar mechirat chametz has like we're
learning all these different קניינים kinyanim. has all these different ways. You
do חליפין chalifin and with כסף kesef and with this and with
that because there's all these questions about what effects קניינים kinyanim. for
non-Jews, what effects קניינים kinyanim, for Jews, what effects קניינים kinyanim between
Jews and non-Jews. So it's not always the same. So therefore תוספות
says all things being equal you're right I mean we do use
it for קידושי אישה, Kiddushei Isha, but all things being equal we'd
rather learn it not from a פסוק pasuk that's between Jews. Yes
Charlie.
The ירמיהו Yirmiyahu פסוק, pasuk, the simplest way to understand it would
be that these are exiles returning to buy land presumably from the
non-Jews who've occupied it.
No,
the context in ירמיהו Yirmiyahu was that God was sort of showing
this to him as a way of symbolizing like the oncoming destruction.
He said you should buy this land to sort of show I
have to remember the exact context but something about showing confidence in
the fact that in the end you'll be exiled and then you'll
come back and so on. It was not it was a very
specific like part of a way of acting out a certain prophecy.
You can take a look at the context. Okay so the גמרא
gemara, says like this.
Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara אמר רב לא שנו אלא
במקום שאין כותבין שטר. Amar Rav lo shanu ela bemakom she'ein kotvin
shtar.
Where is it good that money alone does it? When a document
is not the normal practice to write a document. Going back to
the point before that maybe the פסוק pasuk meant both. So now
we're saying even though the פסוק pasuk doesn't mean both and money
is enough, but very often you do require both. In a place
where it's the practice to always write a document when the land
is sold, okay and presumably what this means מקום שכותבין שטר makom
shekotvin shtar is not that the practice is to recognize that the
transaction doesn't take place without a document. Then it would be much
more obvious. Oh in this place we never consider the transaction to
be finalized unless a document is written, then it's less... oh then
you need a document. That's less of an obvious statement. It seems
he's saying something even more. He seems to be saying that if
it's the standard thing that any possession any transfer of property is
always accompanied
with registering it and writing a document of sale,
even if that's written as a ראיה, raya, but if that always
accompanies it then that becomes a necessary part to do the קניין
kinyan okay because then the presumably because then there's like
no גמר דעת, gemar da'at, there's not a like sense of taking
possession and taking ownership until
you actually these are the normal parts of what of what it's
about, then you don't really have a finalized דעת da'at until those
things are taken care of. So let's take a look.
I mean so it says where is it?
במקום שאין כותבין שטר. Bemakom she'ein kotvin shtar. במקום שכותבין שטר Bemakom
shekotvin shtar where it's normal to have a writ as evidence to
register it a registered writing of the document of it, לא קנה,
lo kana, you don't take possession until the actual writ transfers. And
if you look at רש"י Rashi he says לא קנה. lo kana.
רש"י Rashi says... well actually רש"י Rashi says a little different than
I did. רש"י Rashi, says that מקום שכותבין שטר makom shekotvin shtar
means a שטר מכירה shtar mechira which is a little more of
an obvious statement. So רש"י Rashi says לא שנו, lo shanu, the
previous רש"י, Rashi דקני בכספא לחודיה במקום שאין רגילין לכתוב שטר מכירה.
dekani bechaspa lechuday bemakom she'ein regilin lichtov shtar mechira. So רש"י says
only in a place where it's not the practice to write a
writ of sale. So it sounds like that means that the practice
is to recognize that the writ is part of what effects the
transaction.
וכיון דרגילין בהכי ולא סמכא דעתיה דלוקח עד דנקיט שטרא, d'keivan d'ragilin
b'hachi lo samcha daatei d'lokaya ad d'nakat shtar, דאדעתיה למקני על השטר
ההוא. d'adaiteia l'mikni al hashtar hahu. So Rashi says I think a
more simpler point of saying the statement: if in this place we
all assume that you need a writ to effect the transaction, then
the money won't do it without the writ because we're all working
with the assumption that only the writ is going to effect the
transaction. And then the Gemara continues and says ואי פריש פריש. v'ei
parish parish. But if you explicitly say that you are going to
have the money alone effect the transaction, then it will work because
in principle money alone does work, except if you've changed your expectations
and understandings based on the norms... of the norms. כי הא דרב
אידי בר אבין ki ha d'rav idi bar avin like this is
what Rav Idi bar Avin did: כי זבין ארעא ki zavin ara
when he would buy land, אמר אי בעינא בכספא אקני אי בעינא
בשטרא אקני. amar ei baina b'khaspa ikni ei baina b'shtar ikni. He
would say to the purchaser because obviously the money—well, not obviously here,
but apparently the money would change hands before the document would be
written. It's easier to hand over money, it takes time to write
a document. So he would say: Look, I reserve the right as
the purchaser to decide whether I want the קנין kinyan to take
effect at the time that I handed over the money or at
the time that I get the שטר. shtar. And as long as
you the seller agree to it—you don't have to agree to it,
but as long as you do agree to it—I can choose which
one of those I want to work. Why is it to my
benefit to do that?
Because אי בעינא בכספא אקני דאי בעית למהדר לא מצית הדרת. ei
baina b'khaspa ikni d'ei bayit l'mehadar lo matzit hadrat. If I want,
I can say that the money did it. So therefore the money
changed hands first. So if you want to back out, I have
the right to say: No, I'm not going to let you back
out. I already gave the money. ואי
בעינא בשטרא אקני, v'ei baina b'shtar ikni, and if I want I'll
say the שטר shtar does it, which is going to take like
two weeks later, דאי בעינא למהדר, d'ei baina l'mehadar, so if I
want to back out after the money changed hands, I'd rather be—I
reserve the right to back out. What? Basically, right, it gives me
the opportunity. I can lock it in now and I have the—I
can force you to not back out, and I still have the
option of backing out until the שטר. shtar. Now you gotta admit
that first of all there's like a lot of פשוט חידושים pashut
chidushim here. You know, one is is that the very first part
that, you know, you can change the terms, right? You can basically
say—and this is true a lot in קניינים—I'll kinyanim start by the
fact that you can create your own קניינים. There's something called like
a קנין סיטומתא, kinyan situmta, which basically means that if in a
certain town the merchants have a understood way of signifying when a
transaction is done, you know, let's say it's a handshake, then that
actually
effects the transaction. It's assumed that everybody understands, everybody's committed, there's גמירות
דעת gemirat daat that this action shows that not just that we're
agreeing to the transaction, that the transaction is effected. And ultimately, you
know, you can have a little bit—make your own קנין kinyan. type
of a thing, you know, if there's real גמירות דעת gemirat daat
and that's assumed within a certain community. So given like, you know,
people say like that's like apparently in the diamond industry if you
say מזל וברכה, mazel u'bracha, right, that that's like the signifier that
the deal's done and then you can't back out. I don't know
if you can actually, you know, win that case in secular court,
but if you were to go to a בית דין, beit din,
that would work, okay, because in non-Jewish diamond deals as well. Oh
yeah? I don't know. I think they learned how to say מזל
וברכה. mazel u'bracha. Anyway,
so so, so if that's true, then you can also understand that,
you know, here we're not even creating new קניינים. We're working with
existing קניינים, כסף kessef and שטר, shtar, and we're just sort
of—sort of like—sort of like the other thing we said once before,
you know, about like המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה בדבר שבממון. hamatneh
al mah shekatuv b'Torah b'davar sheb'mamon. You know, you're reshaping it. You're
saying because in this place we're going to assume that you need
both of those to effect the transaction, כסף kessef and the שטר,
shtar, and כסף kessef alone doesn't do it. So that was like
חידוש chidush number one. You know, again, let's say the שטר shtar
was not technically a שטר מכירה. shtar mechira. Let's—this is sort of
the way I was saying it—let's say the שטר shtar was that
we all assume that you have to go ahead and register it
in the county clerk's office, right? So that's a little bit different,
but that's how I was reading the גמרא, Gemara that nevertheless you're
saying like גמירות דעת gemirat daat is not going to happen until
that final thing sort of takes place. And if that's the practice,
then that can hold it off. I think the bigger חידוש chidush
even beyond that is this case of רב אידי בר אבין. rav
idi bar avin. Because like that's giving—we assume transactions are two-sided.
Like, so in a certain context we all agree that it's only
going to be finished, you know, at a certain—as things takes place,
right? But that I have the ability to determine which is the
action, you know, that—I guess I wouldn't describe it as a—as "I
can choose which was the קנין." kinyan I guess I would—It was
agreed. Yeah, but I guess I would describe it as, to me,
it would make more sense to say: I've purchased it now, but
I have the right to retract for the next two weeks, you
know, until this time. Like a right of retraction or, you know,
a right to cancel is a little different to say I get
to choose which was the מעשה קנין. maaseh kinyan. To me that's
like a little funny because a קנין kinyan, is about like—again, I
guess you can say it's a meeting of minds and we've agreed
to sort of like type of a
יש ברירה. yesh breira. Anyway, but that is a little bit strange.
Okay, so now let's continue. ובשטר. u'v'shtar.
So what we're saying is, just so I understand, that whatever the
default of the... Wait so what you're saying is just so I
understand that whatever the default הלכה halacha might be makes no difference
if there's like an accepted practice?
Pretty much yes.
And the ability to change is only on the side of the
buyer?
No presumably the seller could say the same thing. He could say
I get to choose whether it was כסף kesef or שטר, shtar,
you know, like so in this case was it or well the
other side has to agree, it's not a race right? Whoever's more
eager to do the transaction might wind up agreeing. Okay ובשטר. ubish'tar.
So the Gemara says מנלן, menalan, where do you get this from?
אילימא eileima משום דכתיב mishum dechtiv כתבו ספר וחתום והעד עדים kitvu
sefer vechatuum veha'ed edim the same פסוק pasuk by ירמיה Yirmiah ואמרת
ve'amarta שטר ראיה בעלמא. shtar re'aya be'alma. You just said that in
that context פסוק pasuk it was only about you know for to
as evidence. So אלא מהכא ella mehacha ואקח את ספר המקנה. ve'ekach
et sefer hamiknah. It's from the same פרשה parsha but in a
different פסוק pasuk indicates שטר shtar by itself because it calls it
the book of purchase so that it effects the transaction, effects the
purchase, the sale. אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel לא שנו אלא בשטר מתנה.
lo shanu ella bish'tar matanah. When is it? Now we and now
it's the same issue in reverse. When is it that a שטר
shtar without money works? Right? Because you understand what clearly is the
case here is that
because land you don't know who owns it, if there's not a
sense of taking possession, people really want it documented. And that was
the point before that there's like it's hard in many cases money
won't be enough. People don't feel they're confident with it until it's
documented. On the other hand, land often is a serious amount of
money, you know, you take out a mortgage or whatever to pay
for so also the document you could understand also doesn't give you
a sense that it's final until you've got until money has changed
hands. So even though the משנה mishna says כסף kesef is enough
and שטר shtar is enough, the Gemara pushes against that. It says
כסף kesef is only enough unless there's a practice to write a
שטר, shtar, then you need both. שטר shtar is only enough when
we're about to say when it's a מתנה. matanah. But if it's
a מכר, mecher, you also need the כסף. kesef. So most basic
cases you need both כסף kesef and שטר. shtar. Yes.
So this no money down housing deal you can't really...
Well as we discussed before you need at least a פרוטה, prutah,
that gets to the other question. Okay so he says לא שנו
lo shanu אלא בשטר מתנה. ella bish'tar matanah. That's only by a
writ of gift where there's no money. אבל במכר aval bemecher לא
קנה עד שיתן דמים. lo kanah ad sheyiten damim. But with a
sale you have to actually give the money. Okay again and the
way רש״י Rashi explains it is pretty much a גמירות דעת gmirat
da'at issue, right? Obviously the שטר shtar works because it works by
מתנה. matanah. But if you're expecting money and you haven't got money
you don't feel confident enough and there's a lack of גמירות דעת.
gmirat da'at. So the Gemara says מתיב רב המנונא. meitiv Rav Hamnuna.
Rav Hamnuna challenges. בשטר כיצד, Bish'tar keitzad, we have a ברייתא braita
that says how do you do it with a שטר? shtar? כתב
לו על הנייר או על החרס, katav lo al haniyar o al
hacheres, you write on a piece of paper or even on a
piece of pottery, which raises questions because that's forgeable but let's say
עדי מסירה כרבי אלעזר edei mesira k'Rabbi Elazar or whatever has all
questions about whether you need עדים edim by a שטר מכירה shtar
mechira אף על פי שאין בהם שוה פרוטה af al pi she'ein
bahem shaveh prutah even if the piece of paper isn't worth a
פרוטה prutah so don't try to confuse it with כסף kesef שדי
מכורה לך שדי נתונה לך sadi mechurah lach sadi netunah lach you
write on it my field is sold to you or my field
is given to you הרי זו מכורה ונתונה. harei zu mechurah unetunah.
That works, that effects a sale or the gift. So you see
we're talking about מכר mecher and it says that the שטר shtar
works by itself. הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה, hu motiv lah
vehu mefarek lah, he asks the question and then he came up
with an answer. במוכר שדהו מפני רעתה. bemocher sadehu mipnei ra'atah. That
would be a special case.
Yes if you're desperate to sell your field, your field is a
bad field, you're desperate to sell it, right? It's really it's you
know it's been on the market your house for like five years
and finally you found somebody who's willing to buy it. In that
case you don't need the money to change hands. There's גמירות דעת
gmirat da'at and you'll take the money later. Okay but in another
case where there's a good market for it then there's no גמירות
דעת gmirat da'at until you get the money in the pocket. So
that makes the thing clear it's not technically you know it's an
act of קנין kinyan? that needs two technical points. No שטר shtar
is the act of קנין. kinyan It works by מתנה, matanah, it
works when you're desperate to sell the field. But in cases where
you're not desperate we assume that you are reserving your דעת da'at
and you're not you know you yourself have not finalized it in
your own mind until you get the money. Okay by the way
here there's also a debate of the פוסקים poskim of the ראשונים
rishonim about do you need all the money or not. And here
in particular you might think ironically that here maybe you do need
all the money because here if the issue is גמירות דעת gmirat
da'at what is a פרוטה prutah going to do for your גמירות
דעת? gmirat da'at? Right? So here you might really need to get
all the purchase price if I'm reserving you know my גמירות דעת
gmirat da'at in this type of a case. Okay but anyway that's
the similar type of a question. Okay but anyway so well let
me finish it. והוא מותיב והוא מפרק במוכר שדהו מפני רעתה. vehu
motiv vehu mefarek bemocher sadehu mipnei ra'atah. רב אשי אמר Rav Ashi
amar במתנה ביקש ליתנה לו ולמה כתב לו לשון מכר כדי לייפות
את כוחו. bematana bikaish litnah lo v'lamah katav lo lashon mecher kidei
leyapot et kocho. He rereads the ברייתא. braita. He says it's not
talking about two scenarios either שדי נתונה לך sadi netunah lach or
שדי מכורה לך. sadi mechurah lach. It's talking about one scenario. I'm
giving you a gift of my field but in that document so
there's no money changing hands, it's a gift. But in that document
I'm writing שדי מכורה לך. sadi mechurah lach. Why would I call
it a מכר mecher if it's a gift? Because let's say my
creditor comes and collects that field because of a debt. If it
was just a gift I'd say alright it was a gift what
do you want from me you know easy come easy go. But
if it were a sale and a creditor took it you could
ask me... to be to compensate you, not ask, you could demand
that I compensate you. Okay, so if I give you a gift,
but I describe it also as a sale, שדי נתונה לך שדי
מכורה לך, shadi netuna lach shadi mechura lach, it was a gift,
but I'm describing it as a sale. What I am doing is
I am giving you the right to come back to me to
compensate you for it if it gets seized by a creditor. I'm
a very generous guy. Not only am I giving you a field,
but I'm actually giving you the right to collect from me if
that field was seized. Anyway, he makes it a special case. But
basically, the גמרא Gemara now comes down that money, if the practice
is to write a שטר, shtar, money doesn't do it, you need
a שטר, shtar, and even and if you write a שטר shtar
and it's not a special case, then you also need the money.
So in the bottom line is, in most cases, you really need
both because of גמרא דעת Gemara Da'as issues. Each one is the
act of the קנין, kinyan but most cases because of גמרא דעת,
Gemara Da'as, you need the other one to accompany it.
He's just arguing what the default would be if you didn't specify
anything essentially. One more time? No, no, this is just the default.
Let's say we don't know, then alright, it was the כסף kesef
or whatever it is, but that's what they're saying. In other words,
what is the halachic default
if the parameters of the case were unclear? If the parameters of
the case were clear, it's whatever the parameters of the case are.
Yeah, right, right, right. So he's just arguing what's the default.
Well, but it's being מחדש mechadesh that in a vast many many
cases you're going to need both and you have to be aware
of those issues. The other thing to say about a שטר מכר
shtar mecher is that how do we conceptualize a שטר? shtar? Often
a שטר shtar I've been saying is like you want it documented
because how else do you prove that it's yours? Okay, but the
other issue is... I mean, that's the other issue. If you're thinking
about the range of cases where a שטר shtar works: קידושין, Kiddushin,
עבד, Eved, גיטין, Gittin, here. A way of conceptualizing a שטר, shtar,
one way could be the ראיה raya in the שטר shtar effects
the transaction. Since you can prove you're married, prove you're divorced, prove
I own it, that written proof effects the transaction. But you'll notice
that this did not mention any עדים. edim. It just said you
write on it. And it mentioned writing on a piece of pottery.
Pottery can be forged, right? Can scrape it away. So it's quite
possible that when you're not dealing with גיטין Gittin and קידושין, Kiddushin,
which need עדים כדבר שבערוה, edim k'davar she'be'erva, the nature of a
שטר shtar is not a ראיה. raya. You can have a שטר
קנין shtar kinyan without it being able to serve as a proof.
What it is is it's a written expression of my דעת. da'as.
I am concretizing my דעת da'as by writing it down and giving
it to you. So it's basically that that's the... it's like the
word made real. Okay? But it is not because it now can...
you can prove anything. You can't prove it. It's a piece of
pottery, it wasn't signed, there wasn't witnesses. Okay? But because I wrote
it and gave you a written expression, that effects the transaction. So
it's a very important way of thinking about what שטר shtar could
be, what a שטר מכירה shtar mechira could be. Okay, and now
we go to
חזקה, chazaka, ובחזקה. ub'chazaka.
מנלן, Minalan, where do you know this? אמר חזקיה אמר קרא: Amar
Hizkiyah amar kra: ושבו בעריכם אשר תפשתם בה, Ushvu be'areichem asher tafastem
ba, אשר תפשתם. asher tafastem.
Dwell in the cities that you have seized. במה תפשתם? Bameh tafastem?
How do you seize the cities? בישיבה, Bishiva, just dwelling in it.
דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא: D'vei Rabbi Yishmael tanna: וירשתם אותה וישבתם בה.
Virishtem osa viyashavtem ba. You shall inherit, you shall
take possession of it and dwell in it. במה ירשתם? Bameh yerishtem?
And in which way do you take possession? בישיבה, Bishiva, just by
dwelling. Okay, it's actually interesting the difference between קדושה ראשונה Kedusha Rishona
and קדושה שנייה Kedusha Shniya of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. The רמב"ם
Rambam says קדושה ראשונה Kedusha Rishona was על ידי כיבוש מלחמה al
yedei kibbush milchama because they sort of seized it in war. But
the קדושה שנייה, Kedusha Shniya, they were given the right by the
king
of Persia
to return, so they didn't seize it, they just settled in the
cities and the settling was a קנין חזקה. kinyan chazaka. The רמב"ם
Rambam calls it a קנין חזקה, kinyan chazaka, the קנין kinyan of
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the second time, that's קדושה שנייה. Kedusha Shniya.
Now, the interesting thing though is that, so conceptually you get it.
So what would I therefore say that that means to חזקה? chazaka?
I would say I guess it means to take up residence in
a place, right? But that's not what... yeah, and how much time
and whatever. I mean, some sense of your settling yourself, your... now
if it's a field of wheat, you don't settle in the field.
But I guess I would say harvesting the wheat or doing planting
or something of that nature. Anyway, let's take a look because we're
going to see what the act of חזקה chazaka is and exactly
how it's conceptually the same as this idea of ישיבה yeshiva is
not 100% clear to me.
But ישיבה yeshiva must take some time, right? Meaning if you just...
I understand so right away.
That's why I put it out there, so let's take a look
at what חזקה chazaka is. Okay, we'll get back to the act
of חזקה chazaka in a minute. ושאין להם אחריות אין נקנין אלא
במשיכה. Veshe'ein lahem achrayus ein niknin ela bimeshicha. Things that don't have
אחריות, achrayus, that is not land, is with משיכה. meshicha Okay, as
we said, animals maybe are something a little bit different, maybe מסירה,
but basically and it's משיכה. meshicha By the way, משיכה meshicha is
not to exclude הגבהה. הגבהה is always great. הגבהה always works. Okay,
so מנלן? minalan?
Where do you know that that general chattel is with משיכה? meshichah
דכתיב: Dechtiv: וכי תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך או קנה מיד עמיתך. Vechi timkru
mimkar l'amitecha o kano miyad amitecha. When you sell a sale to
your friend or you purchase something. And although the larger context in
the פסוקים psukim there is about selling land, that's the איסור issur
of אונאה ona'ah of overcharging, and ironically חז"ל Chazal say that the
איסור issur of אונאה ona'ah does not apply by land, it only
applies by chattel. So they understand that this פסוק pasuk of making
a sale, again... If you look in the פסוקים psukim in בהר,
Behar, it's talking in the context of land, they understand that it's
talking about chattels, okay, and it describes the sale by that you
take something from the hand of your friend. דבר הנקנה מיד ליד,
Davar hanikna miyad l'yad, something that transfers from hand to hand. So
it's that transfer of possession, that משיכה, meshicha that taking onto you,
which is the קנין. kinyan? Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says that's
very nice if you say that that's דאורייתא d'Oraisa that משיכה meshicha.
works by chattels. ורבי יוחנן דאמר דבר תורה מעות קונות v'Rabbi Yochanan
d'amar dvar Torah maos kohnos but there's the position of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia that says biblically by chattels
it's money, it's not the physical taking of possession. מאי איכא למימר
Mai ika l'meimar so what can you say? You're obviously not going
to prove it from a פסוק passuk because he said it's all
rabbinic, משיכה. meshicha. פיין תנא תקנתא דרבנן קתני. Fein, tana takanta d'Rabbanan
katani. Fine, so then our משנה mishnah telling you the דרבנן הלכה
d'Rabbanan halacha and then you don't need a פסוק, passuk, the דרבנן
הלכה. d'Rabbanan halacha. Now I just want to say something because we're
talking about the conceptual reason about why these קניינים are different, about
why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says if דאורייתא d'Oraisa money works, you
need to actually take possession. And he basically says for the following
reason, and this has to do again with the difference between chattels
and land. Let's say Michael gave me a thousand dollars for a
shipment of, I don't know, of whatever, of wheat. And then I
said to Michael, "Michael, you know what? Terrible thing happened. There was
an accident and all the..." exactly, the whole, all the wheat, it
burned down, I'm sorry, you're out your money. Now even if I'm
not lying, right, the point is is that as long as, even
if I'm a שומר, shomer, you could say I'm a שומר shomer
for his object, okay, but I'm שומר חנם, shomer chinam, I'm שומר
שכר, shomer sachar, like it's, you know, he doesn't want me to
be in possession of his object and be holding on to it
even if I have some liability towards it. If he bought it,
right, he's, you know, it's not in his interest that it should
be his until he can take possession of it. And therefore we
said that until you do משיכה meshicha for רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
you know, it doesn't work. Okay, now that, now that is again
something that is very different than land. Land, right, there's no way
of actual physical taking of possession, it's always there. So as long
as you gave the money, if you want the land, go get
it, it's always there to be gotten. Okay, so again it's, it
makes it clear that something that can move, being in my control
is the biggest demonstration that it's mine, being in my house, I
took it and so on, and actually there's something that is makes
it very problematic that it's my thing under your control. So that's
why it's very much about משיכה meshicha. and הגבהה, whereas by land,
where it's not really there is not that reality of being under
control, you go to other things, you go to כסף, kesef, שטר,
shtar, כסף kesef and שטר, shtar, both of which don't really are
really about the act of the transaction, they're really not about being
control. שטר shtar maybe you could think about being control in the
sense that if it's a שטר ראיה, shtar re'ayah, so it's an
evidence about whose it is, that's a degree of demonstrating control, but
more it's about the act of the transaction. The one thing that
is a degree of control is this idea of חזקה, chazakah, which
we're going to get back to. Yes.
In regarding משיכה, meshicha? you can do משיכה meshicha, on like part
of it and affects the rest of it? It's like with the
wheat. I don't have to be מושך moshech every single grain of
wheat, do I?
Yeah, you do. I mean if it's all in a box, you
might be able to do a little משיכה meshicha on the box.
What if it's ten bushels of wheat?
What am I supposed to do, lift every single one of them
up?
Okay, and if let's say something happens to half of it, then
I can say it's not mine, even though I gave you the
money for it, and I did משיכה meshicha on half of it,
it burns down, I can say, "Reuven, listen, I'm sorry, half of
it burned down, and I didn't do משיכה meshicha on the rest
of it, it's your loss."
Yep. Okay,
so I mean if it's all in a box and you do
a little, and we'll see something like that in a minute, if
it's all in a box and you do a little משיכה on
the box, you might not have to totally displace the box. Okay,
נכסים שאין להם אחריות. Nechasim she'ein lahem achrayus. Now
we're going to get back to this idea that you can do,
take, do one along together with the other, okay, if you sell
land, then the מטלטלין metaltelin can come with it. So let's take
a look. מנא הני מילי? Mina hani mili? Where do you know
that if you do a קנין on land of כסף, kesef, שטר,
shtar, and חזקה, chazakah, you can also transfer מטלטלין metaltelin with it?
אמר חזקיה אמר קרא, Amar Chizkiyah amar kra, ויתן להם אביהם מתנות
V'yiten lahem avihem matanos and he gave them various gifts עם, im,
together with ערי מצורות ביהודה, arei metzuros b'Yehudah, walled cities in Yehudah.
So they came together with it, which means that so by taking
possession of the walled cities, they got the gifts that came together.
Now here's the big question: איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they raised the
question: בעינן צבורין או לא? Be'inan tzuburin o lo? Do you need
them to be piled in the on the plot of land or
not? Okay, now you obviously now first of all you obviously understand
conceptually why you would want them to be piled. If you sort
of say it's a package, you take possession of the land and
you can say you take possession of the land and it's like,
and you know you're selling a furnished house, right, you take possession
of the land and everything that's on the land, it all comes
together as a package. If it's not on the land, what difference
does it make that I bought a little plot of land here
in Minnesota, that I should take possession of your, of your Jaguar
right over in France? Right, like what does that have to do?
Okay, so somehow you could say because land is such a big
קנין, right, obviously clearly it's like the weightier, קרקע, karka, you know,
is a sense of a permanence or whatever, that somehow it's like
if I have the degree of גמירת דעת gemiras da'as to be
קונה koneh land, then... Things that are more trivial can be considered
to be also included in the מעשה קנין. maaseh kinyan. But it's
conceptually it's a lot easier if they're on the land itself. They're
all one bundle. Now, here's the question, if that's true why this
is called a קנין אגב, kinyan agav, by the way, not in
the משנה because you know it's an Aramaic word, but אגב agav
means sort of, you know, together with. So the question is, if
it has to be on the land, why do you need a
קנין אגב? kinyan agav? Why don't I just, why am I not
just קונה koneh because of a קנין חצר? kinyan chatzer? I took
possession of the house, and then your furniture was in now it's
my house, so I take and you want to sell me your
furniture, so I take possession of it because it's in my yard,
right? Why do you need a קנין אגב, kinyan agav, why not
just have it as a קנין חצר? kinyan chatzer? Is that clear
what that question is? Yes? Okay, so.
Does it make a difference?
Well, yeah, I mean, it could make a difference. Well, first of
all, the first difference is why is it being introduced as some
type of קנין? But we can come up with differences. But the
basic answer that the ראשונים rishonim say is קנין חצר kinyan chatzer
only works if it's a חצר משתמרת, chatzer mishtameres, if it's protected
property. So in the case of the house you're right, I don't
need a קנין אגב. kinyan agav. If you want to sell me
your furniture with the house, then after, you know, it's like conceptually
a split second after I own the house, I own the furniture
because it's now in my house.
But if
it's in my field of wheat, which is not protected and not
guarded, okay, there's no קנין חצר kinyan chatzer there. And nevertheless, there's
this קנין of אגב. agav. So that's just important to distinguish. And
the question is, does it have to be on the property to
be seen as a package, or because קרקע karka is such a
weighty type of קנין such a, you know, conceived as the much
bigger deal, then I can just piggyback stuff on together with it.
So בעינן צבורין עליו? bein tziburim alov? Do you need it to
be piled or not? אמר רב יוסף תא שמע Amar Rav Yosef
tashma come and hear.
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, קרקע כל שהוא, karka kol shehu,
even the smallest amount of land, חייבת בפאה, chayaves b'peah, you'd have
to give פאה. peah. Of course, ירושלמי Yerushalmi basically says that it
can't be the smallest amount because you would need two stalks. You'd
need to do a קצירה ketzirah and then leave something over for
the פאה. peah. So it says, well, maybe you had one stalk
that had like five ears coming out of it. So you harvested
one ear, the other ears were פאה. peah. Anyway, the smallest amount
of land is חייב בפאה, chayav b'peah, ובביכורים, u'v'bikurim, and by ביכורים
bikurim you could say האדמה שנתת לי, ha'adama she'nasata li, okay, you'd
have to bring ביכורים bikurim from wheat because a tree would require
much more space. Okay, ולכתוב עליה פרוזבול, v'lichtov aleha pruzbul, you can
only write a פרוזבול, pruzbul, right, to prevent שמיטה shemitah from annulling
the debt. So you can only write it if the borrower has
קרקע. karka. Because the logic is, well, one way of explaining it
is that a standard loan
has קרקע karka to collect from and הלל Hillel only made his,
right, you wouldn't lend money if you didn't have a lien on
the property and הלל Hillel only made his תקנה takanah when there
is in standard loans. So if the borrower has property I can
write a פרוזבול pruzbul and entitle me to collect after שמיטה, shemitah,
otherwise I can't. Another way of conceptualizing it is because one of
the logics of why פרוזבול pruzbul works is that it's based on
the פסוק pasuk of אשר יהיה לך את אחיך תשמט ידך. asher
yihiye lecha es achicha tishmet yadecha. The money that's owed to you,
you know, you should let, you know, you have to relieve the
debt. So if I can hand it over to בית דין, beis
din, it's not money owed to me. But another relevant aspect is
the idea that it's, what's the
פסוק, pasuk, trying to remember the פסוק, pasuk, but anyway, it's something
that has yet to be collected and not something that is so
much considered to be already in my possession. So for example, if
I have collateral, the שמיטה shemitah doesn't doesn't like annul the debt
because it's already to some degree under my control, under my possession.
So land is a little bit like that because because I have
liens on the land, right, the money out there to be from
my debt to be collected from is already to some degree accessible
to me and I have liens on that land. So that's another
way where it limits the ability of שמיטה shemitah to annul. So
when הלל Hillel made his פרוזבול, pruzbul, he wanted it to have
these other qualities to it that help explain why שמיטה shemitah would
not annul it. Yes?
And just having trouble understanding what the difference is between that and
just a normal debt. It isn't.
So it's true, a normal debt שמיטה shemitah does annul. However, there
is some discussion in the גמרא Gemara that maybe actually if it's
a debt with a שטר shtar and with a קנין אחריות kinyan
achrayus written into the שטר, shtar, maybe actually שמיטה shemitah like wouldn't
annul it. Okay, but normally, let's assume that a normal debt שמיטה
shemitah would, but nevertheless, it's on a continuum of it's closer to
the concept of something being like already collected. It's not yet there,
that's why you need the פרוזבול, pruzbul, but it's closer. So if
something is an oral debt and there's no evidence or there's no
land or there's no whatever, it's much more out of my reach
than the land. So you're right, land isn't enough by itself, but
it's closer. Okay, so you need a smallest bit of land to
write a פרוזבול, pruzbul, and then here gets why it's relevant for
us, ולקנות עמה נכסים שאינם אחריות, v'liknos imah nechasim she'einam achrayus, and
with the smallest bit of land, you can transfer that land and
transfer with it
נכסים שאינם אחריות, nechasim she'einam achrayus, chattel. Okay, so now if you
need the chattel to be piled on in the land, how much
chattel can you pile in a square inch of land, in a
כלשהו? kolshehu? Okay, so גמרא Gemara says
ואמרת בעינן צבורין, ve-amarta be-inan tzibburin, if you need it piled in
the land, כלשהו למאי חזי? kolshehu le-mai chazi? What can you do
with a little square-square centimeter of land? So okay, תרגמה targumah money
is bigger than a square centimeter. So תרגמה רב שמואל בר ביסנא
קמיה דרב יוסף, targumah Rav Shmuel bar Bisna kamei de-Rav Yosef, Shmuel
bar Bisna said in front of Rav Yosef, כגון שנעץ בה מחט.
kegon she-na'atz bah machat. Oh, you have a needle in the, you
know, vertical, you know, in the land. So in order to be
מקנה makneh the needle, you can do this small bit of land.
So he said,
oh, we're getting there. So he
said, אמר ליה רב יוסף קבסטן. amar lei Rav Yosef kavastan. So
Rav Yosef said to this word, Rashi says this word means like
you're, you know, you're causing us a headache. Rashi says you're, you
know, you're causing me anguish. אי חבלתנא לאשמעינן מחט? ee chavaltana lashminan
machat? The תנא Tanna is going to tell me something to tell
me about how to transfer needles? Like you, you know, like if
you're selling a כלשהו, kolshehu, then you wouldn't say that if the
whole relevance is for a needle. Now the point is, I'm not
so sure. Because the point is, I just want to establish the
legal principle. The legal principle is there's no minimum amount of land
to do a קנין אגב. kinyan agav. It's true whatever you're selling
has to be piled in the land, but other than that there's
no minimum. So if you can sit something in a tiny bit
it works, if you need bigger to fit it, but the principle
is there's no fundamental minimum to the land, there's just a requirement
of צבורין. tzibburin. So I really don't see there as a problem
at all, but he says ah, you would never say this if
the only נפקא מינא nafka mina is a needle. So the answer
is, אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, or Rav Sheshet said back,
מאן לימא לן דלא תלה בה מרגניתא דשויה אלפא זוזי? man leima
lan de-lo tala bah marganita de-shavya alfa zuzei?
No, maybe on my needle I hung from the needle like a
pearl that was worth a thousand זוז! zuz! So it's not trivial
to tell me I can do a needle. Which I suppose means
the point that I was saying, which is it's the legal principle
that's important. And yes, you're going to teach me even the smallest
amount of land, whatever you can fit, that's your business. Okay, so
that does not prove the issue. תא שמע, ta shema, come and
hear. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, מעשה במדוני אחד, ma'aseh be-Madoni
echad, there was a story of a certain person from this place
of
Madon, שהיה בירושלים, she-hayah bi-Yerushalayim, he was in Yerushalayim, שהיו לו מטלטלין
הרבה. she-hayu lo metaltelin harbeh. He had a lot of chattel. וביקש
ליתנם במתנה, u-vikesh litnam be-matanah, and he wanted to give them as
a gift. אמרו לו, amru lo, people said to him, אין לו
תקנה, ein lo takanah, there's no way to solve this situation, to
transfer all this chattel as a gift, which might be your case.
Like if you have a thousand sheep, what are you going to
do, do a משיכה on each sheep? You know, how do you
do קניינים on all this chattel? So here's... here's what you got
to do. עד שיקנה על גבי קרקע, ad she-yikneih al gabei karka,
transfer them through land. That'll be a quick way to transfer all
of your chattel. Okay, מה עשה, mah asah, what did he do?
הלך ולקח בית סלע. halach ve-lakach beis sela. He bought a בית
סלע. beis sela. Now the סלע sela is a coin, so the
גמרא's Gemara going to first understand what that means is either it
means, Rashi has two explanations, either it means a little plot of
land the size of a
coin, okay, or Rashi says maybe it's from the word a סלע
sela as a rock and it means like a pointed rock, but
nevertheless something that's presumed to have like not any real surface area
to it. סמוך לירושלים, samuch li-Yerushalayim, near Yerushalayim, ואמר, ve-amar, צפוני זה
לפלוני, tziphoni zeh li-ploni, the north of this field will go to
so-and-so, ועמו, ve-imo, and transfer with it, מאה צאן, me'ah tzon, a
hundred sheep, ומאה חביות, u-me'ah chaviyot, and a hundred barrels of wine,
ומת, u-meis, and then he died, וקיימו את דבריו, ve-kiyemu es devarav,
and they said, okay, it was a good sale. Okay, he obviously
did some קנין on the field, you know, on the field. Now
the גמרא Gemara has the following question, one minute. ואי אמרת בעינן
צבורין, ve-ee amarta be-inan tzibburin, if you however need it to be
piled בה, bah, בית סלע למאי חזי? beis sela le-mai chazi? How
can you pile all that stuff either on a tiny plot of
land or on a top of a rock, a pointed
rock? Right? גמרא Gemara says מי סברת בית סלע סלע ממש? mi
savrat beis sela sela mamash? What makes you think we're talking literally
a סלע? sela? Again, Rashi has two explanations, either a coin or
a rock, a pointed, you know, a pointed rock. No, מאי סלע
דנפיש טובא? mai sela de-nafish tuva? No, no, no, סלע sela meant
it was a large plot of land. ואמאי קרו ליה סלע? ve-amai
karu lei sela? Why did they call it a סלע? sela? דקשי
כסלע, de-kashi ke-sela, it was hard land, that's why. You know, he
was only buying it, he was only buying it to effect the
transaction. So he's not going to buy good fertile land, right? He
bought a plot of a big plot of, you know, hard, unusable
land and then he used it to effect the transaction. Fine. Okay,
but אי הכי נמי, ee hachi nami, the stuff was on
it. Of course it does not sound that way from the ברייתא.
braita. It sounds like you transfer a little bit of land, you're
able to transfer other stuff with it. תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, de-amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav,
מעשה באדם אחד, ma'aseh be-adam echad, a story with this certain man,
שחלה בירושלים, she-chalah bi-Yerushalayim, he grew... he was sick in Yerushalayim, meaning
he was on his deathbed. Now the question before we move any
further that the גמרא Gemara interrupts with is, if he's on his
deathbed, why do you need to do a particular type of a
קנין? We have the general words that the words of somebody on
their deathbed effect the transaction themselves. So the גמרא Gemara says either
we're talking כרבי אליעזר, ke-Rabbi Eliezer, that it's... either we're talking that
he was on his deathbed but it's like Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Eliezer
says there's no הלכה halacha of שכיב מרע, shechiv mera, that even
on your deathbed you... you can only transfer transfer with a real
קניין. kinyan. So either the story was he was on his deathbed
and it's according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that you need a
real קניין. kinyan. ואמרי לה V'amri lei or some say בריא הויה
כרבנן bari havah k'rabbanan that he wasn't on his deathbed and therefore
it goes even like the רבנן. Rabbanan. But one way or another
this guy needed to do a real קניין. kinyan. Okay. היו לו
מטלטלין הרבה. Hayu lo metaltelin harbe.
He had a lot of property of cattle. וביקש ליתנם במתנה U'vikesh
litnam b'matana and
he wanted to give them with a gift. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
they said to him, אין לו תקנה עד שיקנם אגב קרקע. ein
lo takana ad she'yaknem agav karka. He can't do that in any
normal way, right? You can't what, lift up every object, do משיכה
on every object? The way to do it is to get some
קרקע. karka. Okay. וביקש ליתנם במתנה, U'vikesh litnam b'matana,
where are we? מה עשה? Ma asa? What did he do? הלך
ולקח בית רובע. Halach v'lakach beit rova. He got the place of
a רובע rova and that actually is a certain measure which is
a רובע הקב rova hakav which is not too big. Okay. But
it's so it's a certain size field, an acre or whatever, a
quarter of an acre, let's say. 104 and 6 square אמה.
ama. 104 and 6 square אמה. ama.
Now you know. 200 feet, about 200 let's say 200 feet by
200 feet. Not a huge plot. Okay. בית רובע. Beit rova. Where
am I? סמוכה לירושלים Samucha l'Yerushalayim ואמר טפח על טפח. V'amar tefach
al tefach. Not only that, he said, a square טפח tefach לפלוני
l'ploni is transferred to so-and-so, ועמו מאה צאן ומאה חביות. v'imo me'ah
tzon u'me'ah chaviut. And with it a hundred sheep and a hundred
barrels of wine. ומת. U'met. What? Explain that. Exactly. וקיימו חכמים את
דבריו. V'kiymu chachamim et devarav. הי אמרת ואינן צבורין, He amarta v'inan
tziburin, and if you think you need piled, טפח
על טפח למאי
חזי?
tefach al tefach
l'mai chazi?
How wait what how are you gonna fit all that stuff on
a טפח tefach? by טפח? So the גמרא Gemara says, ah, we
are gonna explain it to you. הכא במאי עסקינן בדמי. Hacha b'mai
askinan b'damai. He didn't really transfer a hundred sheep and a hundred
barrels of wine. What he did was he put 10,000 dollars of
money in that little square inch of plot. Of course, and why
did he say a thousand barrels of sheep and a thousand barrels
of wine? The amount that it's equivalent to. Maybe he told his
servant, go figure out the amount and put that amount, you know,
in that plot of land. Obviously a very weak answer. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute. Now the גמרא Gemara is
going to finally get to the question of in terms of seeing
is this a viable answer that he put just the money is
the question about why was קרקע karka the only way of doing
this? Aren't there other ways of effecting a transaction? So let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this, הכי נמי מסתברא. Hachi
nami mistabra. You know that makes sense that we're talking about money.
Really? Why? דאי סלקא דעתך Di salka daatach מאה צאן ומאה חביות
me'ah tzon u'me'ah chaviut ממש, mamash, if we're literally talking about sheep
and barrels, so why was it so hard to transfer it? ניקנינהו
ליה בחליפין. Nikninayhu lei b'chalipin. Why couldn't he have just done it
with חליפין? chalipin? You know, you got the guy near you and
you do a קניין סודר kinyan sudar and a קניין סודר kinyan
sudar like works for everything, right? So what's the big problem? Why
did he need קרקע? karka? Just do a קניין סודר. kinyan sudar.
Ah, if it's money, we understand because money
is the one thing that you can't be קונה בחליפין. koneh b'chalipin.
Well, money and women. Okay. So, so therefore, if it was money,
we understand he had no other choice. But if it was the
real objects, well just do חליפין, chalipin, who needed this? So the
גמרא Gemara says, ואלא מאי v'ela mai לדמי? l'damai? So what do
you want to say? You want to say that it was money?
There's other ways to do money. ניקנינהו ליה במשיכה. Nikninayhu lei b'meshicha.
Do a קניין משיכה, kinyan meshicha, right? Have somebody just take the
money even if, even if the guy isn't around, have somebody take
the money for the guy. So do חליפין, chalipin, do so, so
now we've got a question we got to answer besides this issue
of צבורין, tziburin, which is why was it so difficult? Right? If
it was מטלטלין metaltelin do משיכה. If it was מטלטלין metaltelin do
חליפין. chalipin. If it was money do משיכה. Why did he have
to do this קרקע? karka? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא, the
answer must be, דליתיה למקבל מתנה d'leisa l'mikabel matana הכא נמי דליתיה
למקבל מתנה. hacha nami d'leisa l'mikabel matana. The answer must be, you
know why we didn't do it? Because the other party wasn't around
and therefore you couldn't do משיכה and you couldn't do and you
couldn't do חליפין. chalipin. Of course, if the other party isn't around,
you know what else you can't do? You can't do כסף kesef
and you can't do שטר. shtar. You can't do... maybe you could
do חזקה, chazaka, maybe you get the message to him and he
goes and on his own does חזקה. chazaka. Anyway, so let's keep
on working about this. Well we'll see because before that we have
to besides that question we have to say, and if he wasn't
around, so what? Let somebody stand in for him. וניקנינהו ליה אגב
אחר. V'nikneyhu lei agav acher. So let somebody else stand in for
him and do a קניין חליפין, kinyan chalipin, right? Or do a
משיכה. So the answer is, לא סמכא דעתיה. lo samcha daatei. No.
So first of all, רש"י says, if he's not around you understand
why you didn't do חליפין. chalipin. You know why you didn't do
חליפין? chalipin? Because Michael, let's say I'm trying to let's say I'm
trying to sell my sheep to Charlie and Charlie isn't around and
we want to do it by חליפין. chalipin. How would that transaction
take place? And I want you to help out. What would you
have to do? You're representing Charlie. Right, I'd have to give if
it was חליפין, chalipin, it's something that... You would have to give
me something of yours. You don't want to give me something of
yours. So we can't do חליפין chalipin because if the guy isn't
around nobody else wants to volunteer their object. But how about doing,
you know, משיכה? If it's money, take this money and take possession
of it for Charlie. So that answer is, I'm not giving you
the money I want to go to Charlie. I don't trust you.
Okay. So he says, so the גמרא Gemara. says, לא סמכא דעתיה.
lo samcha daatei. I don't... oh, I don't feel confident giving you
the money. סבר שמיט ואכיל להו. Savar shamit v'achil lehu. You'll go
and take the money yourself. Okay. So therefore, therefore we, before getting
to was it money or was it the sheep, we have to
explain why you didn't do something else. So why you didn't do
חליפין chalipin was because nobody
wants to give me their thing to do חליפין.
chalipin. You can give it right back. I know, so it's not
a great answer. Why it wasn't כסף kesef was why it wasn't
משיכה, if we're dealing with if it's dealing with sheep and barrels
we know why it wasn't משיכה because as Michael asked in his
earlier question, you'd have to do it on a thousand barrels. But
if it's money, I just anyway I don't trust him to do
it. So can't do משיכה if it's money, you can't do חליפין
chalipin if it's מטלטלין, metaltelin, so you had to do these other
things. Of course the question now becomes but he's not around Charlie's
not around to do these other things. Ah, but I don't care,
for example, if it was a שטר shtar I just write שדי
נתונה לצ'רלי sadi netuna le-Charlie and I give it to Michael. I'm
not afraid that he's going to pocket the money, right? That just
does it, right?
כסף kesef he
won't give me a dollar for Charlie, but I can write a
שטר. shtar. Okay, so presumably, I mean the גמרא Gemara didn't sort
of spell all that out but presumably that's the answer. So wait,
let's see the גמרא. So now we have these two explanations. We
understand why he didn't do something else and we still don't know
whether we're talking about the money that was צבורין tzivurin or whether
it was the objects and you don't need צבורין. tzivurin. Okay, so
the גמרא says like this. ואלא מאי אין לו תקנה? Ve-ela mai
ein lo takana? What does it mean there was no other way
of solving it? There was a way of solving it, you just
didn't want to use the option, but you could have given, you
know, done a משיכה on the money. הכי קאמר. Hachi kaamar. למי
דלא סמכא דעתיה. Lemi delo samcha daata. No, based on your reservations,
this person did not want to give the money to this third
party. אין לו תקנה אלא אגב קרקע. Ein lo takana ela agav
karka. Then he had to do קרקע. karka. Sure, there was other
ways to do it, but not other ways that this person felt
were viable. So therefore, you know, giving money wouldn't work if it
was the issue of money because you don't trust the guy. Doing
חליפין chalipin wouldn't work because presumably the other people don't want to
participate. Maybe the reason the other people don't want to participate is
they feel this guy's about to die, maybe he'll give it to
me if I don't, anyway who knows. Anyway the other people don't
want to participate, so presumably though קרקע karka could have worked I
guess by שטר shtar and maybe you can get the other people
to participate by שטר. shtar. Yes. So this this discussion is assuming
that I haven't appointed a שליח. shaliach. Is there? No, it's for
your זכות. zechut. It's a מתנה. matana. זכין לאדם שלא בפניו. Zachin
leadam shelo befanav. Oh, okay. Okay, so
we will continue tomorrow to see the resolution about whether you need
צבורין tzivurin or not.
All right.
Thanks.